Guide to the Great Falls Breweries, Inc. Records 1933-1968
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Great Falls Breweries, Inc. Records
1933-1968
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 042
Great Falls Breweries, Inc.
26.7 linear feet 38 archival boxes and 29 oversize volumes
This collection contains correspondence, financial, legal, organizational, and promotional records generated and collected by the Great Falls Breweries, Inc. and its subsidiary, the Montana Malting Company. Collection materials document procedures and finances within the company and professional relationships with product distributors, industry representatives, other regional breweries, suppliers, elected officials, and government regulators.
Historical Note
Great Falls Breweries Inc. was founded by Emil Sick in 1933 immediately after the repeal of Prohibition. It was begun with the purchase of the interests of the Montana Brewing Company and the American Brewing Company, two Great Falls firms dating from the 1890s that had been closed by Prohibition. Mr. Sick continued the operation until 1949 when he sold the property to local interests. It was again sold in 1966 to Blitz-Weinhard Company of Portland, Oregon, which continued operations until September, 1968 when severe economic conditions forced the closure of the Great Falls plant. At the time of its closing, the Great Falls operation was the last operating brewery in the four state area of Montana, Idaho, North Dakota, and Wyoming
This collection contains correspondence, financial, legal, organizational, and promotional records generated and collected by the Great Falls Breweries, Inc. and its subsidiary, the Montana Malting Company. Collection materials document procedures and finances within the company and professional relationships with product distributors, industry representatives, other regional breweries, suppliers, elected officials, and government regulators. These records provide insights into rural Montana brewing businesses in the years following repeal of Prohibition, through the Great Depression, and into the post World War II economic transformations across the American west. Collection materials particularly evidence the impacts on regional (bottle-oriented) breweries precipitated by 1960s canned beer packaging innovations.
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Financial and Legal
Series III: Organization
Series IV: Printed Material
Series V: Montana Malting Company
Series VI: Photographs
Series VII: Artifacts
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and the University of Montana--Missoula. Materials in box 18, folders 6 and 7, box 19, folder 1 are restricted access under Social Security Administration regulations.
The Blitz-Weinhard Company purchased Great Falls Breweries, Inc. in 1966 and suspended Montana operations in 1968. The Blitz-Weinhard Company placed all Great Falls Breweries Inc. records in a storage unit until donation to the Archives.
Gift of Blitz-Weinhard Company, 1970. The remainder, two original stock ledger journals, 1938-1966, now in Series II, Box 40, and 3 copies of stockholder lists, two from 1966 and one from 1967, now in Box 37/12, were donated by Stoel Rives, Attorneys at Law, 2012.
During 2004 reprocessing, 5 folders of general interest publications (all dated 1961) were transferred to the Mansfield Library's Special Collections.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Montana Malting Company
Beer bottles; Beer cans; Beer industry--Montana--Great Falls; Beer industry--West (U.S.); Breweries--Montana--Great Falls; Brewing industry--Montana--Great Falls; Brewing industry--West (U.S.)
Business records--Montana--Great Falls
Montana; Business, Industry, and Labor
- Correspondence, 1933-1968; Series I; 1.0 linear feet
  This series contains incoming and outgoing correspondence related to Great Falls Breweries, Inc. business operations. These materials document procedures and finances within the company and professional relationships with product distributors, industry representatives, other regional breweries, suppliers, elected officials, and government regulators.
  - 1933 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1957 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1958 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - 1959 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - 1960 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - A, 1961 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - B, 1961 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - C, 1961 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - D, 1961 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - E, 1961 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - F, 1961 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Great Falls Breweries Scholarship Fund, 1961 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - G, 1961 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - H, 1961 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - I, 1961 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - J, 1961 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - K, 1961 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - L, 1961 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Montana Various Departments, 1961 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - M, 1961 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - N, 1961 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - O, 1961 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - P, 1961 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Q, 1961 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - R, 1961 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - S, 1961 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - T, 1961 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - U, 1961 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - V, 1961 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - W, 1961 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Y, 1961 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Z, 1961 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - 1962 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - 1963 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - 1964 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - 1965 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - 1966 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - 1967 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - 1968 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - undated (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Interoffice, 1961, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 3/9)
- Financial and Legal, 1933-1968; Series II; 17.7linear feet and 23 oversize volumes
  This series contains financial and legal records generated by Great Falls Breweries, Inc. Among these materials are accounts receivable, audits, inventories, invoices, payroll, stock registers, federal income and alcohol control documents, as well as daily, monthly and annual reports--including a nearly complete sequence of brewery monthly transaction statements from 1933 to 1966. These records document market conditions, supply sources, and management decisions spanning a period of dramatic economic transformation within the brewing industry and across the American west.
  Materials in box 18, folders 6 and 7, box 19, folder 1 are restricted access under Social Security Administration regulations.
  - Accounts Receivable, 1965 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Accounting Records, undated (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Appraisal Report, 1933 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Assets, Liabilities, and Trial Balances, 1966 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Audit Reports, 1933-1939 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Audit Reports, 1940-1945 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Audit Reports, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Audit Reports, 1952, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Audit Reports, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Audit Reports, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Audit Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Audit Reports, P. W. Kuschel and E. G. Sick in Trust, 1933 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Balance Sheets, 1935-1936, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Monthly Beer Count, Select Beer, 1966 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Monthly Beer Count, Big Sky Beer, 1966 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Monthly Beer Count, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Fred Briggs Distribution Company, Financial Statement, 1966 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Cases Shipped, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Checks, copies, 1967 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Checks, copies, 1967 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Depreciation Schedules, 1961, 1963, 1965 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Hospitality Incorporated, local promotion, 1961 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Idaho Beer Tax, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Daily Inventory Report, 1966 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Monthly Inventory, Packaging Materials, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Invoices and Orders, 1952, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Invoices and Orders, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Malt Received, monthly, 1963 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Materials Inventory, 1962-1968 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Montana Quarterly and Annual Withholding Reports, 1962 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Montana Quarterly and Annual Withholding Reports, 1963 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Montana Quarterly and Annual Withholding Reports, 1964 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Montana Quarterly and Annual Withholding Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Montana Quarterly and Annual Withholding Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Montana Quarterly and Annual Withholding Reports, 1967 (Box-folder 6/16)
  - State Return of Income at Source (Dividends), 1962-1963 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Order Books, 1964 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Packaging Department, Statistics and Budget, 1966 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Packaging Department, Statistics and Budget, 1967 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Packaging Department, Statistics and Budget, 1968 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Pay Schedules, 1961-1967 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Purchase by Blitz-Weinhard, 1966 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Receipt Book, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Receipt Book, 1968 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Monthly Sales Comparison, Big Sky Beer, 1966 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Monthly Sales Comparison, 1966 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Sales Comparison, 1961, 1963 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Sales to Great Falls Distributors, 1967 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Sales to Great Falls Distributors, 1967 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Daily Shipping Journal, 1967 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Daily Shipping Journal, 1967 (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Monthly Statements, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1934 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1935 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Monthly Statements, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1938 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1939 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1940 (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Monthly Statements, 1941 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1942 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1943 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Monthly Statements, 1944 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1945 (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1947 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1948 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1949 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Monthly Statements, 1953 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1956 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1957 (Box-folder 14/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1957 (Box-folder 14/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1958 (Box-folder 14/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1958 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1959 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1959 (Box-folder 15/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1960 (Box-folder 15/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1960 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 16/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1962 (Box-folder 16/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1962 (Box-folder 16/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1962 (Box-folder 16/5)
  - Monthly Statements, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 16/6)
  - Monthly Statements, 1964 (Box-folder 16/7)
  - Monthly Statements, 1964 (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Monthly Statements, 1964 (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Monthly Statements, 1964 (Box-folder 17/3)
  - Monthly Statements, 1965 (Box-folder 17/4)
  - Monthly Statements, 1965 (Box-folder 17/5)
  - Monthly Statements, 1965 (Box-folder 17/6)
  - Monthly Statements, 1966 (Box-folder 17/7)
  - Stockholders ledger sheets, 1938-1966 (Box-folder 18/1)
  - Stockholders lists, 1946-1965 (Box-folder 18/2)
  - Stockholders lists, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 37/12)
  - Stock ledger journal, A-K, 1938-1966 (Box-folder 40/1)
  - Stock ledger journal, L-Z, 1938-1966 (Box-folder 40/2)
  - Monthly Transactions at the Brewery (Federal form), 1933-1934 (Box-folder 18/3)
  - Office of Price Administration, Interim Financial Reports, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 18/4)
  - Office of Price Administration, Annual Financial Reports, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 18/5)
  - Federal Income Paid Statements (dividends), [access restricted], 1962-1963 (Box-folder 18/6)
  - Federal Income Paid Statements (dividends), [access restricted], 1964-1965 (Box-folder 18/7)
  - Federal Dividend Income Paid and Employee Withholdings Statements, [access restricted], 1962-1967 (Box-folder 19/1)
  - Withholding tax tables, State and Federal, 1960, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 19/2)
  - Notification of beer to be destroyed, 1966 (Box-folder 19/3)
  - Notification of beer to be destroyed, 1966 (Box-folder 19/4)
  - Notification of beer to be destroyed, 1967 (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Federal Tax Returns, Quarterly and Annual Withholdings, 1962 (Box-folder 19/6)
  - Federal Tax Returns, Quarterly and Annual Withholdings, 1963 (Box-folder 19/7)
  - Federal Tax Returns, Quarterly and Annual Withholdings, 1964 (Box-folder 19/8)
  - Federal Tax Returns, Quarterly and Annual Withholdings, 1965 (Box-folder 19/9)
  - Federal Tax Returns, Quarterly and Annual Withholdings, 1966 (Box-folder 19/10)
  - Federal Tax Returns, Quarterly and Annual Withholdings, 1967 (Box-folder 19/11)
  - Detached Financial Records, 1960-1968 and undated (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Great Falls Breweries Inc., Annual Reports, 1934-1965 (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Distributors Monthly Accounts, 1967 (Box-folder 20/3)
  - Distributors Monthly Accounts, 1968 (Box-folder 20/4)
  - Distributors Monthly Sales and Inventory, 1966 (Box-folder 20/5)
  - Distributors Monthly Sales and Inventory, 1966 (Box-folder 21/1)
  - Distributors Monthly Sales and Inventory, 1967 (Box-folder 21/2)
  - Distributors Monthly Sales and Inventory, 1967 (Box-folder 21/3)
  - Distributors Monthly Sales and Inventory, 1968 (Box-folder 21/4)
  - Weight Certificates, Grain, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 21/5)
  - Lawsuit, Great Falls Breweries and Mack Johnston Inc. vs. Pawson Patent #3, 173, 5864, 1966 (Box-folder 21/6)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #1-297 (Volume 22)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #298-600 (Volume 23)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #601-900 (Volume 24)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #901-1200 (Volume 25)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #1201-1500 (Volume 26)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #1501-1800 (Volume 27)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #1800-2100 (Volume 28)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #2101-2400 (Volume 29)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #2401-2700 (Volume 30)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #2701-3000 (Volume 31)
  - Stock Certificate Books, Certificates #3001-3401 (Volume 32)
  - Accounts Receivable, 1966 (Volume 5)
  - General Ledger, 1933 (Volume 6)
  - General Ledger, 1933-1937 (Volume 7)
  - Voucher Register, 1963-1964 (Volume 8)
  - Voucher Register, 1965-1966 (Volume 9)
  - Voucher Register, 1966 (Volume 10)
  - Voucher Register, 1968 (Volume 11)
  - Monthly Record of Transactions at Brewery, 1934 (Volume 12)
  - Record of Brewery Operations, 1955-1956 (Volume 13)
  - Record of Brewery Operations, 1957-1958 (Volume 14)
  - Record of Brewery Operations, 1959-1960 (Volume 15)
  - Record of Brewery Operations, 1961-1962 (Volume 16)
  - Record of Brewery Operations, 1963-1964 (Volume 17)
  - Daily Stock Report, 1965-1966 (Volume 18)
  - Payroll Register, 1962-1966 (Volume 19)
  - Payroll Register, 1967 (Volume 20)
  - Montana Checks, 1966-1967 (Volume 21)
  - Check Book, Kalispell First National Bank, 1958-1959 (Volume 22)
  - Plant Ledger, 1933-1946 (Volume 23)
  - Stockholders Journal, 1934-1962 (Volume 24)
  - Distribution Journal, 1934-1938 (Volume 25)
  - Monthly Report of Brewery Operations, 1959-1966 (Volume 26)
  - Monthly Brewing Report, 1965-1968 (Volume 27)
- Organization, 1933-1968; Series III; 1.5 linear feet and 4 oversize volumes
  This series contains organizational records generated by Great Falls Breweries, Inc. These records primarily document Board of Directors and shareholder lists and meeting materials. Also included are equipment designs, manuals, and instructions, a brewery floor plan developed during renovations in 1954, and office administration documents.
  - Bylaws and amendments, 1933-1960 (Box-folder 33/1)
  - Board of Directors meeting, 1935 (Box-folder 33/2)
  - Board of Directors meeting, minutes, 1940 (Box-folder 33/3)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 33/4)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 33/5)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 33/6)
  - Stockholders Meetings, 1936, 1940, 1942, 1949 (Box-folder 33/7)
  - Stockholders Meetings, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 33/8)
  - Stockholders Meetings, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 33/9)
  - Stockholder Proxy Lists, undated (Box-folder 33/10)
  - Stockholder Proxies, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 33/11)
  - Stockholder Proxies, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 33/12)
  - Stockholder Proxies, 1952, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 33/13)
  - Stockholder Proxies, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 34/1)
  - Stockholder Proxies, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 34/2)
  - Stockholder Proxies, 1965 (Box-folder 34/3)
  - Equipment Designs and Specifications, undated (Box-folder 35/1)
  - Equipment Brochures and Instructions, 1960-1968 and undated (Box-folder 35/2)
  - Floor Plan for Brewery, 1954 (Box-folder 35/3)
  - Employee Applications, 1961 (Box-folder 35/4)
  - Company Forms, (blank), 1942, 1948-1965 (Box-folder 35/5)
  - Uniforms, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 35/6)
  - Minute Book, I, 1933-1940 (Box-folder OS39/1)
  - Minute Book, II, 1941-1945 (Box-folder OS39/2)
  - Minute Book, III, 1945-1950 (Box-folder OS39/3)
  - Minute Book, IV, 1951-1958 (Box-folder OS39/4)
- Printed Material, 1960-1965; Series IV; 0.25 linear feet
  This series contains a short sequence of brewing industry publications and competitor advertising samples collected by Great Falls Breweries management.
  - Advertising materials, other companies, undated (Box-folder 36/1)
  - Brewery Cost Report, 1958 (Box-folder 36/2)
  - Group Insurance Administration Manual, 1965 (Box-folder 36/3)
  - Uniform Classification of Accounts for the Brewing Industry, 1960 (Box-folder 36/4)
  - Assorted Brewing Industry Publications, 1961 (Box-folder 36/5)
- Montana Malting Company, 1934-1936; Series V; 0.5 linear feet
  This series contains financial and organizational records generated by the Montana Malting Company, a wholly-owned division of Great Falls Breweries, Inc. These records document procedures implemented and challenges faced by the brewery to establish its own, large-scale malting operation intending to expand distribution following the repeal of the 18th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution and related Prohibition laws.
  - Audit reports, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 37/1)
  - Balance sheets, 1936 (Box-folder 37/2)
  - Inventory, 1935 (Box-folder 37/3)
  - Salaries, 1935 (Box-folder 37/4)
  - Sale to Great Falls Breweries, 1936 (Box-folder 37/5)
  - Monthly Statements, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 37/6)
  - Stock Certificate Book, #1-25, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 37/7)
  - Stockholders meetings, 1935 (Box-folder 37/8)
  - Transfer Journal Entries, 1934 (Box-folder 37/9)
  - Minute Book, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 37/10)
- Photographs, undated; Series VI; 3 items
  This series contains three photographs of Great Falls Breweries advertising images. Two images are bottle label designs and the third is a road sign demo.
  - Great Falls Breweries, Inc., Bottle Label Design, undated (Box-folder 37/11, Photo number 42(VI):2)
  - Great Falls Breweries, Inc., Advertising Sign, undated (Box-folder 37/11, Photo number 42(VI):3)
- Artifacts, circa 1930s; Series VII; 2 items
  This series consists of two corporate seal stamps, one each for Great Falls Breweries, Inc. and Montana Malting Company.
  - Great Falls Breweries, Inc. Seal Stamp, undated (Box 38, Artifact number 42(VII):1)
  - Montana Malting Company Seal Stamp, undated (Box 38, Artifact number 42(VII):2)